{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The Alma-Ata Protocols were signed in the wake of this event, and one man’s proclamation of the “Sinatra Doctrine” encouraged this event. One leader was imprisoned in his dacha at Foros prior to this event, which led to the formation of the CIS. The ascension of Boris Yeltsin marked the end of, for ten points, what event which led to the independence of Ukraine, Belarus, and many other countries?",
      "answer": [
        "Dissolution of the USSR",
        "synonyms for dissolution,",
        "Soviet Union for USSR"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Jonathan Baldwin Turner advocated for the creation of more of these institutions in the 1850s. The Smith-Lever Act was implemented to allow greater cooperation between these institutions and their surroundings, and HBCUs are examples of these institutions that were established for African-Americans after the Civil War. The Morrill Land-Grant Acts set aside land for the creation of these institutions, including one in Champaign, Illinois. For ten points, name these educational institutions, including Iowa State, Cornell, and MIT.",
      "answer": "colleges or universities"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader is depicted in the Catalan Atlas sitting on a throne and inspecting a gold nugget. This leader commissioned the Djinguereber [jin-gah-ray-bear] Mosque and Sankore University, both located in Timbuktu, and he caused a massive deflation of the price of gold in Cairo while on an extravagant Hajj to Mecca. For ten points, name this Mali emperor, or Mansa, who ruled from 1312 to 1327.",
      "answer": "Mansa Musa or Musa I"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote a cantata beginning “Eternal source of light divine” to celebrate Queen Anne’s birthday. This composer wrote four coronation anthems, including Zadok the Priest, for another British monarch who asked this composer to write a piece celebrating the end of the War of the Austrian Succession. For ten points, name this Baroque composer of the Music for the Royal Fireworks, as well as the oratorio Messiah.",
      "answer": "George Frideric Handel"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization donated the SMS Goeben to the Ottoman Navy, and a rebellion by this organization in Kiel led to the end of the empire it served. Alfred Tirpitz sought to reform this organization, which used wolfpacks to attack British convoys. This organization made heavy use of the doctrine of unrestricted submarine warfare, and was led through WWII by Admiral Karl D¨onitz. For ten points, name this navy which used U-Boats during the two World Wars.",
      "answer": "German Navy"
    },
    {
      "question": "One speech given in this location referenced a John Magee poem, noting that seven people, including Ronald McNair, had “slipped the surly bonds of Earth to touch the face of God.” After a meeting in this location, Elvis Presley was given a badge for the Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs. A photograph taken in this location shows a child playing beneath the Resolute Desk, Richard Nixon called the Apollo 11 astronauts from, for ten points, what room located in the West Wing in the White House?",
      "answer": "Oval Office"
    },
    {
      "question": "Leo Strauss argued that “Modern” philosophy began with this man, who used Hannibal and Scipio Africanus as examples of brutal rulers. The author of Ab Urbe Condita, the Roman historian Livy, inspired a discourse by this author, who encourages the title figure of another work to emulate both the lion and the fox. “It is better to be feared than loved” according to, for ten points, what Italian author of The Prince?",
      "answer": "Niccolo Machiavelli"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Sullivan-Hoey law was passed in response to this incident. This event helped spur the growth of the ILGWU after the “Uprising of 20,000.” This event started on the eighth floor of the Asch building, whose main exits were locked on orders of the owners, Max Blanck and Isaac Harris. 146 mostly-female garment workers died in, for ten points, what 1911 fire that consumed a New York sweatshop?",
      "answer": "Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "The United Kingdom almost joined this war after its fishermen were mistaken for warships in Dogger Bank by the Baltic Fleet. This war’s aftermath led to Sergei Witte’s [VIT-uh’s] industrializtion efforts and the October Manifesto. It began inconclusively at Port Arthur, and was ended, with Theodore Roosevelt’s assistance, by the Treaty of Portsmouth. For ten points, name this 1904-05 war between countries led by Tsar Nicholas II and Emperor Meiji.",
      "answer": "Russo-Japanese War"
    },
    {
      "question": "Strict adherence to this religion’s teachings caused the death of Elli Perkins by her schizophrenic son. This faith uses the acronym MEST to describe the physical universe, which can be controlled by Operating Thetans who have undergone “auditing” and the use of E-meters. In this religion, the Supreme Galactic Overlord Xenu detonated hydrogen bombs in volcanoes, as described by the science fiction author of Dianetics. For ten points, name this religion, founded by L. Ron Hubbard and practiced by people such as John Travolta and Tom Cruise.",
      "answer": "Church of Scientology"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "P.G.T. Beauregard successfully repelled Union attacks on this state’s Bermuda Hundred. Joseph Hooker was forced to retreat from Banks’ Ford at the Battle of Chancellorsville in this state. This state’s secession from the Union was rewarded when the Confederacy moved its capital from Montgomery to this state. The final surrender of Robert E. Lee’s army of this state was conducted at Appomattox Court House in, for ten points, what Southern state with capital at Richmond?",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This 1864 battle during the Siege of Petersburg near Richmond was a Confederate victory and is named for the result of a mine detonated by Ambrose Burnside.",
        "answer": "Battle of the Crater"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ion Pacepa, a 3-star general from this nation, defected to the United States during the Cold War, the highest-ranking Eastern bloc defection. This nation was joined with Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia in the Little Entente. One leader of this country succeeded Georghe Georghiu-Dej, and promulgated the July Theses; that leader and his wife were executed by firing squad on Christmas Day, 1989. For ten points, name this Eastern European country that was ruled by Nicolae Ceausescu [cho-CHESS-ku].",
        "answer": "Romania"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ceausescu’s Decree 770 was intended to have this result, which was analyzed by Steven Levitt in Freakonomics. Romania’s abortion policy was tightened as a result of that decree.",
        "answer": [
          "increasing Romania’s population",
          "equivalents"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This game was played at BC Place on artificial turf after a lawsuit requesting natural grass was droppped. A 60-yard strike over Ayumi Kaihori in the 16th minute was the fourth of seven goals in this game, in which Christie Rampone and Abby Wambach subbed on in the second half. A hat trick by Carli Lloyd sealed, for ten points, what 2015 soccer tournament won by the United States over Japan?",
        "answer": [
          "2015 FIFA Women’s World Cup final match",
          "equivalents describing the championship game of the 2015 FIFA Women’s World Cup"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This USA goalie won the 2015 Women’s World Cup Golden Glove as the top goalie in the tournament, shortly after having been suspended from the team for her domestic violence arrest.",
        "answer": "Hope Solo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s Karakoy neighborhood is home to the Genoese-built Galata Tower. This city’s historic peninsula contains the Sarayburnu outcropping and lies south of the Golden Horn. The Marmaray Tunnel connects this city’s western and eastern halves. This city’s Topkapi Palace was built by Mehmed II, who also converted its Hagia Sophia into a mosque. For ten points, what city was known as Constantinople until it was conquered by the Ottoman Turks?",
        "answer": [
          "Istanbul",
          "Constantinople before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Istanbul lies on this strait connecting the Sea of Marmara to the Black Sea, making it an important historical stop for wheat shipments to the Mediterranean Sea.",
        "answer": "Bosporus or Bosphorus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "For inventing a procedure that treated diseases of this organ, Antonio Egas Moniz won the 1949 Nobel Prize in Medicine. Phineas Gage’s injury of this organ led to new breakthroughs in its study. Ancient Egyptians attributed this organ’s function to the heart and removed it through the nostrils before mummification. Lobotomies remove part of, for ten points, what component of the central nervous system encased within the skull?",
        "answer": [
          "brain",
          "frontal lobe and prefrontal cortex"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Trepanation, a historical medical procedure thought to help brain ailments such as epilepsy and headaches, involved performing this pressure-relieving action.",
        "answer": [
          "cutting a hole in the skull",
          "any similar description"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “Plan West” defensive scheme was unsuccessful during this campaign, and the Battle of Mokra during this campaign saw a cavalry charge successfully repel a tank advance. The Gleiwitz incident was used as a pretense by one side in this conflict to launch an attack, and the “Phony War” followed this action. The Free City of Danzig was annexed after, for ten points, what September 1st, 1939 offensive that marked the beginning of World War II?",
        "answer": "Invasion of Poland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The invasion of Poland was facilitated by a Pact signed by Joachim von Ribbentrop and this man, the foreign minister of the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": "Vyacheslav Molotov"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A museum named for Tuol Sleng commemorates those who died at the hands of this party after it won a civil war against Lon Nol. This party called its state Democratic Kampuchea, and it created tens of thousands of mass graves in the Killing Fields. For ten points, name this communist movement led by Pol Pot which ruled Cambodia in the 1970s.",
        "answer": "Khmer Rouge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Khmer Rouge lost power in Cambodia after a failed invasion of this neighbor country in 1978. This country’s village of Ba Chuc was the site of a Cambodian massacre in that invasion.",
        "answer": "Socialist Republic of Vietnam"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s son James was killed by members of the Shawnee tribe, sparking Dunmore’s War, and his son Israel was killed at the Battle of Blue Licks. This friend of Simon Kenton was briefly captured by Blackfish in 1778. A John Filson book created a series of myths about, for ten points, what frontiersman who helped settle Kentucky by blazing a trail through the Cumberland Gap?",
        "answer": "Daniel Boone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Daniel Boone blazed this road through the Cumberland Gap to link Kentucky to the east.",
        "answer": "Wilderness Road"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Colonial America",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "colony founded by Roger Williams, now the smallest U.S. state.",
          "answer": "Rhode Island and Providence Plantations"
        },
        {
          "question": "colony home to Paul Revere, which was governed as a state by John Hancock and Samuel Adams.",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "body that appointed George Washington to lead the army.",
          "answer": "Second Continental Congress"
        },
        {
          "question": "African-American man who was the first person to die in the Boston Massacre.",
          "answer": "Crispus Attucks"
        },
        {
          "question": "period of religious revival among church members that occurred in the 1730s and 1740s.",
          "answer": "First Great Awakening"
        },
        {
          "question": "Puritan woman that was expelled from Massachusetts Bay Colony after the Antinomian Controversy.",
          "answer": "Anne Hutchinson or Anne Marbury"
        },
        {
          "question": "1754 meeting in New York where Benjamin Franklin drew the “Join or die” cartoon.",
          "answer": "Albany Congress"
        },
        {
          "question": "unfair three-word political concept that James Otis equated with tyranny.",
          "answer": "taxation without representation"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The European Union",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "country led from Ankara that has long tried to join the EU.",
          "answer": "Republic of Turkey"
        },
        {
          "question": "2009 treaty, named for the capital of Portugal, that overhauled the EU.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Lisbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Balkan country with capital Zagreb that joined in 2013.",
          "answer": "Croatia"
        },
        {
          "question": "award won by the EU in 2012 for their efforts in representing human rights.",
          "answer": "Nobel Peace Prize"
        },
        {
          "question": "two commodities pooled in a common market by a predecessor to the EU.",
          "answer": [
            "coal and steel",
            "European Coal and Steel Community"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "treaty that established the European Union in 1993.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Maastricht"
        },
        {
          "question": "German co-architect of that treaty, who led the Christian Democrats and served as Chancellor of re-unified Germany.",
          "answer": "Helmut Kohl"
        },
        {
          "question": "area, named for a Luxembourg town, in which EU citizens can travel between other member states without a passport.",
          "answer": "Schengen Area"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "South America",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "nation whose capital city, Montevideo, hosted the first FIFA World Cup.",
          "answer": "Uruguay"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Argentina who was married to Evita.",
          "answer": "Juan Domingo Peron"
        },
        {
          "question": "man, known as “El Libertador,” who founded Gran Colombia and conquered Ecuador.",
          "answer": "Sim´on Jos´e Antonio de la Santisima Trinidad Bolivar y Palacios"
        },
        {
          "question": "country currently led by Nicolas Maduro, chosen by a socialist who died in 2013.",
          "answer": "Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "country whose Golden Law outlawed slavery in 1888.",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "man who overthrew Salvador Allende [eye-EN-day] in 1973.",
          "answer": "Augusto Jose Ramon Pinochet Ugarte"
        },
        {
          "question": "country with whom the U.S. wanted to sign the Hay-Herran Treaty regarding ownership of Panama.",
          "answer": "Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "nation where members of the Peoples Temple Agricultural Project committed mass suicide in 1978.",
          "answer": "Guyana"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country repelled the forces of Eleftherios Venizelos after they landed at Smyrna, in accordance with the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Sevres that divided this country’s immediate predecessor. This country’s independence was guaranteed by the Treaty of Lausanne, and it saw reforms based on the Six Arrows of its first leader, who adopted Latin script, banned (10 pts)",
        "fezzes, and deposed the Sultan. For ten points, name this country, formed from the remnants of the Ottoman Empire by Kemal Ataturk, which has its capital at Ankara."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Turkey"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one speech, this man compared interviewing Jesse Jackson to boxing a glacier, then told his audience, “enjoy that metaphor, because your grandchildren will have no idea what a glacier is.” A character played by this man frequently used the nickname (20 pts)",
        "“Papa Bear” to refer to Fox News host Bill O’Reilly. “Americans for a Better Tomorrow, Tomorrow” was a super PAC founded by this comedian, who coined the term (10 pts)",
        "“truthiness” on the first episode of his namesake spin-off of The Daily Show. For ten points, name this former host of a Report on Comedy Central, the current host of CBS’s Late Show."
      ],
      "answer": "Stephen Colbert"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The novels No Longer Human and The Setting Sun are characteristic of the “I-novel” style developed in this country in the 1940s. The short story “Patriotism” follows the aftermath of a coup in this nation; the same author wrote a fascist play, (20 pts)",
        "My Friend Hitler, before his death in an attempted coup d’etat in 1970. The burning of the (10 pts)",
        "Golden Pavilion in this country inspired a 1956 novel narrated by Mizoguchi. The authors Osamu Dazai and Yukio Mishima are from, for ten points, what Asian country?"
      ],
      "answer": "Japan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Suffragette Mary Richardson slashed a painting by this man, whose Portrait of Pope Innocent X is distorted in Francis Bacon’s Screaming Pope series. This artist painted (20 pts)",
        "Justin of Nassau giving a key to General Ambrogio Spinola after a military defeat and a goddess looking at herself in a mirror held by (10 pts)",
        "Cupid. This artist of The Surrender of Breda and The Rokeby Venus showed himself painting a large canvas in a work commissioned by King Philip IV of Spain as a portrait of the Infanta Margarita and her maids. For ten points, name this Spanish painter of Las Meninas."
      ],
      "answer": "Diego Rodriguez de Silva y Velazquez"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This successor of Johnny Torrio claimed that a war wound, rather than Frank Gallucio’s knife, inspired his nickname. Despite ordering the (20 pts)",
        "killings of dozens of men, probably including the seven killed in the St. Valentine’s Day Massacre, he was only convicted of (10 pts)",
        "tax evasion. For ten points, name this man, nicknamed “Scarface,” who led the Chicago mob during Prohibition."
      ],
      "answer": "Alphonse Gabriel “Al” Capone"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This nation’s southern border was established by the Treaty of Taif. One city here is completely off-limits to non-practitioners of its state religion, the most influential sect of which in this country is (20 pts)",
        "Wahhabism. Concerns have recently arisen over the spread of the MERS virus among pilgrims in this country during the annual (10 pts)",
        "Hajj. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern kingdom whose capital is Riyadh, home to the two holiest cities of Islam, Medina and Mecca."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Saudi Arabia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s government was defeated by a promise to create a universal National Health Service under Labour Party leader Clement (20 pts)",
        "Attlee, whom this man suggested would need “a Gestapo” to implement his plans. This man proclaimed “I have nothing to offer but blood, (10 pts)",
        "toil, tears, and sweat” upon taking office in 1940, shortly before Germany began “the Blitz” against his country. For ten points, name this British Prime Minister during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Winston Churchill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Peter Williamson, one of these people, was captured by Native Americans and returned to England as “Indian Peter” in the 18th century. A practice known as “blackbirding” is sometimes used to (20 pts)",
        "acquire these people. A “redemptioner” policy allowed these people to buy their freedom after a determined (10 pts)",
        "number of years, commonly seven. For ten points, name this practice where people paid for passage to the New World in exchange for a period of forced service, which was banned with slavery by the 13th Amendment."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Indentured servants",
        "word forms"
      ]
    }
  ]
}